A Guide to the Papers of James Lawrence Cabell, 1882-1974
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Papers of James Lawrence Cabell, 1882-1974
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-35
1 box, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 0.5 linear feet, 38 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Wilhelm Moll, Director of the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for many years, apparently collected the documents.
Biographical Information
James Lawrence Cabell was born August 26, 1813 in Nelson County, Virginia. He attended private schools in Richmond, matriculated at the University of Virginia in 1829, and earned his A.M. in 1833. The following year he continued the study of medicine at the University of Maryland and obtained his M.D degree. To further his education he went to Paris until 1837 when he was offered the chair of anatomy, physiology, and surgery at the University of Virginia. He remained in this capacity until 1856 when a chair of anatomy and material medica was created. He continued to teach physiology and surgery, and for a time comparative anatomy, until the end of the 1888-89 session. He was appreciated for his devotion to teaching and was also an able diagnostician.
In addition to his more than 50 years of service to the University of Virginia, Dr. Cabell was in charge of the Confederate States Military Hospital in Charlottesville during most of the Civil War. A member of the Medical Society of Virginia, he was elected president in 1876. He was the organizer and served from 1879-1884 as the first president of the National Board of Health which was created by an Act of Congress on March 3, 1879. In that year he was also president of the American Public Health Association.
Dr. Cabell married Margaret Gibbons in 1839. He had no biological children but adopted two nieces. He died August 13, 1889 in Albemarle County, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The collection contains three original letters from Dr. Cabell, a biographical sketch, interlibrary loan documents, a paper written by Wilhelm Moll about two of Dr. Cabell's letters, a bibliography of Dr. Cabell's writing, and reprints of those documents.
Arrangement
The box is arranged into two parts. The first section is arranged chronologically with Cabell's original letters and information concerning Cabell. The second section contains photocopies of Cabell's papers and addresses. These are arranged chronologically by publication date.
Contents List
- Letter from J. L. Cabell to My dear Friend, Dr. C. R. Agnew 1882 July 17, 1 ALS 1p. (Box-folder 01-001)
  Letter refers to the opposition of Representative Cox to the general principles of the N.B.H. [National Board of Health] due to the bitterness of Cox towards the personnel of the N.B.H.
- Letter from J. L. Cabell to My dear Friend 1884 February 5, 1 ALS 4pp. (Box-folder 01-002)
  Cabell is concerned about a sudden distressing situation of stuffing in his right ear and is frightened about the prospect of impending deafness. He seeks medical advice. The letter is probably written to Dr. Cornelius Agnew who was a professor of ophthalmology and otology.
- Letter from J. L. Cabell to My Dear Friend [Dr. Cornelius R. Agnew] 1885 November 17, 1 ALS 3pp., 1 TD 2pp. (Box-folder 01-003)
  Cabell writes about the death of his sister.
- Biographical sketch of James Lawrence Cabell [1920], 1 TD photocopied 2pp. (Box-folder 01-004)
- Interlibrary loan documents 1973-74, 10 D 10pp.. (Box-folder 01-005)
  The documents relate to Dr. Wilhelm Moll's attempt to obtain a copy of a report given by Cabell from the National Library of Medicine.
- "Two Letters by Dr. James Lawrence Cabell" by Wilhelm Moll, "Virginia Medical Monthly," Vol 101. 1974 January, 1 TD 3pp. (Box-folder 01-006)
  Moll writes about letters written in 1979 by Cabell to Dr. Cornelius Agnew.
- "Writings of the Original Fellows" ND, 2 TD with AN 4pp. (Box-folder 01-007)
  Includes a bibliography of James Lawrence Cabell's work.
- Letter on duke Medical Center Library stationary with enclosed copies of notes signed by J. L. Cabell 1876-77, 1 ANS 1p.3 ANS photocopied 3pp. (Box-folder 01-008)
- "Etiology of Enteric Fever" by J. L. Cabell 1877, 1 TD photocopied 49pp. (Box-folder 01-009)
- Address to the American Public Health Association by J. L. Cabell 1877, 1 TD photocopied 2pp. (Box-folder 01-010)
- "Address in State Medicine and Public Hygiene" by J. L. Cabell 1878, 1 TD photocopied 33pp. (Box-folder 01-011)
- Annual Address to the Public Health Association by J. L. Cabell 1879, 1 TD photocopied 23pp. (Box-folder 01-012)
- "Salicylic Acid in the Treatment of Enteric Fever" by J. L. Cabell [1879], 1 TD photocopied 3pp. 1TD with AN carbon copy 1p. (Box-folder 01-013)
- "The American Public Health Association and the Withers Bill" by J. L. Cabell 1879, 1 TD photocopied 2pp. (Box-folder 01-014)
- "Brief Notice of the Rise and Progress of International Hygiene" by J. L. Cabell 1881, 1 TD photocopied 16pp. (Box-folder 01-015)
- "The National Board of Health and the International Sanitary Conference of Washington" by J. L. Cabell 1881, 1 TD photocopied 19pp. (Box-folder 01-016)
- A Brief Historical Notice of the Origin and Progress of International Hygiene" by James L. Cabell 1881, 1 TD photocopied 19pp. (Box-folder 01-017)
- "Annual Report of the National Board of Health, with Statement of Expenditures, for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1881" by J. L. Cabell 1881 November 19, 1 TD photocopied 12pp. (Box-folder 01-018)
- "The National Board of Health" by J. L. Cabell 1882, 1 TD photocopied 4pp. (Box-folder 01-019)
- "On Sanitary conditions in Relation to the Treatment of Surgical Operations and Injuries" by James L. Cabell 1882, 1 TD photocopied 41pp. (Box-folder 01-020)
- "A Review of the Operations of the National Board of Health" by J. L. Cabell 1882, 1 TD photocopied 31pp. (Box-folder 01-021)
- "Proper Mode of Reducing Partial Forward Dislocation of the Sternoclavicular Joints" by J. L. Cabell 1883, 1 TD photocopied 1p. (Box-folder 01-022)
- "Remarks on the Treatment of Acute Pneumonia" by J. L. Cabell 1883, 1 TD photocopied 6pp. (Box-folder 01-023)